<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [

<!ENTITY geography_support
"<inlinemediaobject>
	<imageobject><imagedata fileref='images/internet.png' /></imageobject>
 </inlinemediaobject>
">
 
<!ENTITY Z_support
"<inlinemediaobject>
	<imageobject><imagedata fileref='images/cube.png' /></imageobject>
 </inlinemediaobject>
">
]>
<book lang="en">
	<bookinfo>
		<title>Introduction to MobilityDB</title>

		<author>
			<firstname>Esteban</firstname>

			<surname>Zim&aacute;nyi</surname>

			<affiliation>
				<orgname>Universit&eacute; libre de Bruxelles, Belgium</orgname>
			</affiliation>
		</author>

		<pubdate>01.09.2019</pubdate>
		<abstract>
			<para>MobilityDB is an extension to the PostgreSQL object-relational database system and its spatial extension PostGIS. It allows temporal and spatio-temporal objects to be stored in the database, that is, objects whose attribute values and/or location evolves in time. MobilityDB includes functions for analysis and processing of temporal and spatio-temporal objects and provides support for GiST and SP-GiST indexes.</para>

			<para><inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref='images/mobilitydb-logo.png' width='200px' /></imageobject></inlinemediaobject></para>
		</abstract>
	</bookinfo>

	<chapter id ="introduction">
		<title>Introduction</title>

		<para>MobilityDB is an extension of <ulink url="http://postgresql.org">PostgreSQL</ulink> and <ulink url="http://postgis.net">PostGIS</ulink> that provides temporal types. Such types are data types that represent the evolution on time of values of some element type, called the base type of the temporal type. For instance, temporal integers may be used to represent the evolution on time of the number of employees of a department. In this case, the data type is &ldquo;temporal integer&rdquo; and &ldquo;integer&rdquo; is the base type. Similarly, a temporal float may be used to represent the evolution on time of the temperature of a room. As another example, a temporal point may be used to represent the evolution on time of the location of a car, as reported by GPS devices. Temporal types are useful because representing values that evolve in time is essential in many applications, for example in mobility applications. Furthermore, the operators on the base types (such as arithmetic operators and aggregation for integers and floats, spatial relationships and distance for geometries) can be intuitively generalized when the values evolve in time.</para>

		<para>MobilityDB provides the following temporal types: <varname>tbool</varname>, <varname>tint</varname>, <varname>tfloat</varname>, <varname>ttext</varname>, <varname>tgeompoint</varname> and <varname>tgeogpoint</varname>. These temporal types are based, respectively, on the <varname>bool</varname>, <varname>int</varname>, <varname>float</varname>, and <varname>text</varname> base types provided by PostgreSQL, and on the <varname>geometry</varname> and <varname>geography</varname> base types provided by PostGIS (restricted to 2D or 3D points).<footnote><para>Although 4D temporal points can be represented, the M dimension is currently not taken into account.</para></footnote> Furthermore, MobilityDB uses four time types to represent extents of time: the <varname>timestamptz</varname> type provided by PostgreSQL and three new types which are <varname>period</varname>, <varname>timestampset</varname>, and <varname>periodset</varname>. In addition, two range types are defined in MobilityDB: <varname>intrange</varname> and <varname>floatrange</varname>.</para>

		<sect1 id ="workshop_materials">
			<title>Workshop Materials</title>
				
			<para>This workshop uses a <ulink url="data/mobilitydb_workshop_2019.zip">data package</ulink>. Download it and extract to a convenient location. There are two types of data in the package:
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
                        <para>GIS data from Berlin extracted from <ulink url="https://www.openstreetmap.org">OpenStreetMap</ulink>. It includes the road network and points of interest.</para>
                    </listitem>
					<listitem>
                        <para>Mobility data generated with <ulink url="http://dna.fernuni-hagen.de/secondo/BerlinMOD/BerlinMOD.html">BerlinMOD</ulink>, a benchmark for spatio-temporal database management systems. BerlinMOD provides a data generation that can be customized. The data in the package has been generated over the OSM road network for Berlin at a scale factor of 0.005.</para>
                    </listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
            </para>

            <para>All the data in the package is public domain and freely redistributable. All the software used in the workshop is open source, and freely redistributable. This workshop is licensed as Creative Commons <ulink url="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/us/">share alike with attribution</ulink>, and is freely redistributable under the terms of that license.</para>

            <para>This workshop is heavily inspired from and builds upon the workshop <ulink url="https://postgis.net/workshops/postgis-intro/">Introduction to PostGIS</ulink>. This workshop assumes therefore that you have a knowledge of GIS in general and PostGIS in particular.</para>

        </sect1>

		<sect1 id ="workshop_links">
			<title>Links to have on hand</title>

				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
                        <para>PostGIS: <ulink url="http://postgis.net/">http://postgis.net/</ulink></para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                            <para>Docs: <ulink url="http://postgis.net/docs/">http://postgis.net/docs/</ulink></para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </listitem>
					<listitem>
                        <para>PostgreSQL: <ulink url="http://www.postgresql.org/">http://www.postgresql.org/</ulink></para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                            <para>Docs: <ulink url="http://www.postgresql.org/docs/">http://www.postgresql.org/docs/</ulink></para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </listitem>

					<listitem>
                        <para>PgAdmin: <ulink url="http://www.pgadmin.org/">http://www.pgadmin.org/</ulink></para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                            <para>Docs: <ulink url="https://www.pgadmin.org/docs/pgadmin4/latest/index.html">https://www.pgadmin.org/docs/pgadmin4/latest/index.html</ulink></para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </listitem>
					<listitem>
                        <para>QGIS: <ulink url="http://qgis.org/">http://qgis.org/</ulink></para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                            <para>Docs: <ulink url="https://qgis.org/en/docs/index.html">https://qgis.org/en/docs/index.html</ulink></para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </listitem>
				</itemizedlist>

        </sect1>
	</chapter>

</book>
