<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
   ****************************************************************************
    MobilityDB Manual
    Copyright(c) MobilityDB Contributors

    This documentation is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-Share
    Alike 3.0 License: https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/
   ****************************************************************************
-->
<appendix xml:id="temporal_parquet">
	<title>TemporalParquet: a Parquet Footer Convention for Temporal Types</title>
	<para>
		Apache Parquet has become the de-facto interchange format for columnar analytics data on object storage. Geospatial data has had a documented Parquet convention — <ulink url="https://geoparquet.org/">GeoParquet</ulink> — since 2022; mobility data (trajectories, temporal types, spans, sets) has not. This appendix documents <emphasis>TemporalParquet</emphasis>, the convention MobilityDB adopts for storing temporal columns in Parquet files: a <varname>BYTE_ARRAY</varname> column carrying MEOS-WKB encoded values, with a JSON metadata object in the Parquet file footer that describes each column's encoding, base type, subtype, and (where applicable) SRID, geodetic flag, or H3 resolution.
	</para>

	<para>
		The convention is the file-format substrate of the <emphasis>Temporal Data Lake</emphasis> architecture (RFC <ulink url="https://github.com/MobilityDB/MobilityDB/pull/912">#912</ulink>) and is consumed in production by MobilityDuck (DuckDB extension) and MobilitySpark (Apache Spark binding). The same <varname>.parquet</varname> shard written by one platform reads back losslessly on the other two.
	</para>

	<sect1>
		<title>File Structure</title>
		<para>
			For every column carrying a MobilityDB temporal type, the column is <varname>BYTE_ARRAY</varname> with logical-type <varname>NONE</varname>; each row value is the MEOS-WKB encoding of the temporal value; NULLs are encoded as Parquet NULLs.
		</para>
		<para>
			The Parquet file's <varname>key_value_metadata</varname> carries an entry with key <varname>temporal</varname> whose value is a JSON document:
		</para>
<programlisting>
{
  "version": "1.0.0",
  "primary_temporal_column": "traj",
  "columns": {
    "traj": {
      "encoding": "MEOS-WKB",
      "encoding_version": "1.0",
      "base_type": "tgeompoint",
      "subtype": "Sequence",
      "interpolation": "linear",
      "srid": 4326,
      "geodetic": false,
      "has_z": false
    }
  }
}
</programlisting>
		<para>
			The <varname>temporal</varname> object coexists with GeoParquet's <varname>geo</varname> object: a single file can have both.
		</para>
	</sect1>

	<sect1>
		<title>Type Coverage</title>
		<informaltable frame="all">
			<tgroup cols="3">
				<thead>
					<row>
						<entry>MobilityDB type</entry>
						<entry><varname>base_type</varname> value</entry>
						<entry>Notes</entry>
					</row>
				</thead>
				<tbody>
					<row>
						<entry><varname>tbool</varname>, <varname>tint</varname>, <varname>tfloat</varname>, <varname>ttext</varname></entry>
						<entry>same</entry>
						<entry>Scalar temporals.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry><varname>tgeompoint</varname>, <varname>tgeogpoint</varname></entry>
						<entry>same</entry>
						<entry><varname>srid</varname>, <varname>geodetic</varname>, <varname>has_z</varname> populated.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry><varname>tgeometry</varname>, <varname>tgeography</varname></entry>
						<entry>same</entry>
						<entry>General spatial-temporal.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry><varname>th3index</varname></entry>
						<entry><varname>th3index</varname></entry>
						<entry>First cross-platform extended type. Carries optional <varname>h3_resolution</varname>; see <xref linkend="tp_th3index"/>.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry><varname>tcbuffer</varname>, <varname>tnpoint</varname>, <varname>tpose</varname>, <varname>trgeo</varname>, <varname>tpcpoint</varname>, <varname>tpcpatch</varname></entry>
						<entry>each as its own <varname>base_type</varname></entry>
						<entry>Remaining extended temporal types; bindings ship in subsequent releases following the <varname>th3index</varname> reference shape.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry><varname>stbox</varname>, <varname>tbox</varname></entry>
						<entry>same</entry>
						<entry>Bounding boxes.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry><varname>intspan</varname>, <varname>floatspan</varname>, <varname>tstzspan</varname>, spansets, sets</entry>
						<entry>each as its own <varname>base_type</varname></entry>
						<entry>Spans, spansets, sets.</entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</informaltable>
		<para>
			The <varname>subtype</varname> field applies only to lifted temporal types (<varname>Instant</varname> / <varname>Sequence</varname> / <varname>SequenceSet</varname>); span / set / box columns omit it.
		</para>

		<sect2>
			<title>Type-Specific Optional Fields</title>
			<para>
				Some <varname>base_type</varname> values may carry optional metadata that lets consumers decide whether the column is usable for a given workload <emphasis>without decoding any row</emphasis>:
			</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para><varname>srid</varname> — EPSG code of the column's CRS. Required for spatial-temporal types.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para><varname>geodetic</varname> — <varname>true</varname> ⇒ spheroidal-metre math (Haversine / Vincenty); see <xref linkend="tp_geodetic"/>.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para><varname>has_z</varname> — column carries a Z dimension throughout.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para><varname>h3_resolution</varname> — applies to <varname>th3index</varname>. Optional integer in <varname>[0, 15]</varname> declaring every cell in the column was produced at this resolution. Consumers MAY rely on it to gate cell-membership prefilters (cross-join probes via <varname>everEqH3IndexTh3Index</varname>) without decoding any row.</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</sect2>

		<sect2 xml:id="tp_geodetic">
			<title>Geodetic Distances</title>
			<para>
				<varname>tgeompoint</varname> stores coordinates in the input CRS (e.g. lon/lat WGS-84) and computes <emphasis>Euclidean</emphasis> distances in that coordinate space; <varname>length(tgeompoint)</varname> over a WGS-84 trajectory therefore returns degrees, not kilometres.
			</para>
			<para>
				<varname>tgeogpoint</varname> is the geodetically-correct variant: it carries the same MEOS-WKB bytes but with the geodetic flag set in the type tag, causing MEOS to route all spatial math through the spheroidal Haversine / Vincenty engine — lengths and speeds are in <emphasis>metres</emphasis>.
			</para>
			<para>
				When writing TemporalParquet files that consumers will use for distance or speed analytics, prefer <varname>tgeogpoint</varname> (set <varname>"geodetic": true</varname> in the column metadata). The geodetic flag is self-describing in MEOS-WKB: a file written with <varname>asBinary(tgeogpointSeq(...))</varname> reconstructs as a geodetic sequence on any platform that calls <varname>tgeogpointFromBinary(blob)</varname>.
			</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 xml:id="tp_th3index">
		<title>Worked Example: <varname>th3index</varname></title>
		<para>
			<varname>th3index</varname> is the first <emphasis>extended</emphasis> temporal type to ship a cross-platform binding pair. The MEOS-WKB encoder handles the <varname>th3index</varname> payload identically to <varname>tbigint</varname> (both lift over an <varname>int64</varname>); the metadata <varname>base_type</varname> is the discriminator. The companion <varname>h3_resolution</varname> field declares uniform resolution per column so consumers can gate cell-membership prefilters without scanning the data.
		</para>
		<para>
			Example footer entry for a BerlinMOD trips table:
		</para>
<programlisting>
{
  "version": "1.0.0",
  "primary_temporal_column": "trip",
  "columns": {
    "trip": {
      "encoding": "MEOS-WKB",
      "encoding_version": "1.0",
      "base_type": "tgeompoint",
      "subtype": "Sequence",
      "interpolation": "linear",
      "srid": 4326,
      "geodetic": false,
      "has_z": false
    },
    "trip_h3": {
      "encoding": "MEOS-WKB",
      "encoding_version": "1.0",
      "base_type": "th3index",
      "subtype": "Sequence",
      "interpolation": "step",
      "h3_resolution": 7
    }
  }
}
</programlisting>
		<para>
			The companion <varname>trip_h3</varname> column is produced once at load time via <varname>tgeompoint_to_th3index(trip, 7)</varname> and acts as a cheap cell-membership prefilter on subsequent cross-join queries that runs unchanged on MobilityDB, MobilityDuck and MobilitySpark:
		</para>
<programlisting>
-- BerlinMOD Q5 (nearest-approach) with the th3index prefilter
SELECT t1.licence AS licence1, t2.licence AS licence2,
       nearestApproachDistance(t1.trip, t2.trip) AS d
FROM   Trips t1 JOIN Trips t2 ON t1.vehId &lt; t2.vehId
WHERE  everEqTh3IndexTh3Index(t1.trip_h3, t2.trip_h3)
  AND  nearestApproachDistance(t1.trip, t2.trip) IS NOT NULL;
</programlisting>
		<para>
			<varname>interpolation</varname> is always <varname>step</varname> for <varname>th3index</varname> (a vehicle is in exactly one cell at a time); <varname>subtype</varname> follows the source <varname>tgeompoint</varname>'s subtype after the lifted conversion. The <varname>h3_resolution</varname> field is the consumer-side hint that lets a reader gate the prefilter without decoding any row.
		</para>
		<note>
			<title>Soundness note (2026-05-11)</title>
			<para>
				The current <varname>tgeompoint_to_th3index</varname> implementation samples one cell per source instant; cells traversed by the trip's straight-line segment between consecutive instants are not visited. Until the <varname>fix/th3index-srid-flags-lift</varname> branch and the prefilter-soundness follow-ups land, <varname>trip_h3</varname> is an <emphasis>under-sampling</emphasis> of the true cell set, and any prefilter built on it may miss true hits.
			</para>
			<para>
				The TemporalParquet metadata schema is unaffected — <varname>base_type: "th3index"</varname> and <varname>h3_resolution</varname> describe the bytes regardless of how the column was produced. Consumers who need strict semantic correctness must run the underlying <varname>tgeompoint</varname> predicate without relying on the prefilter as a <varname>WHERE</varname> clause; treat the prefilter as a future optimisation tracked by the th3index port chain (MobilityDB PRs #807, #866, #938 plus the pending fix branch).
			</para>
		</note>
	</sect1>

	<sect1>
		<title>Encoding Versioning</title>
		<para>
			<varname>encoding_version</varname> is <varname>MAJOR.MINOR</varname> of the MEOS-WKB schema. New WKB tags (e.g. when a future temporal type lands) bump <varname>MINOR</varname>; breaking layout changes bump <varname>MAJOR</varname>. Readers MUST refuse files with a higher <varname>MAJOR</varname> than they support; readers MAY accept higher <varname>MINOR</varname> by skipping the unrecognised tags.
		</para>
	</sect1>

	<sect1>
		<title>Reference Implementation</title>
		<para>
			A Python reference implementation ships in <varname>scripts/parquet/</varname> (RFC POC PR <ulink url="https://github.com/MobilityDB/MobilityDB/pull/831">#831</ulink>): <varname>tp_export.py</varname> writes annotated TemporalParquet files, <varname>tp_import.py</varname> reads them back, and <varname>tp_inspect.py</varname> dumps the footer metadata. A round-trip regression test lives at <varname>mobilitydb/test/io/queries/090_temporalparquet_roundtrip.test.sql</varname>.
		</para>
		<para>
			The convention spec itself, beta-testing guide, and the cross-platform port history live in <varname>doc/temporal-parquet/</varname>; this appendix is the user-facing summary.
		</para>
	</sect1>

	<sect1>
		<title>Related</title>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>RFC <ulink url="https://github.com/MobilityDB/MobilityDB/pull/911">#911</ulink> — TemporalParquet convention (this appendix's source).</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>RFC <ulink url="https://github.com/MobilityDB/MobilityDB/pull/912">#912</ulink> — Temporal Data Lake (edge-to-cloud architecture; this convention is the file-format substrate).</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>PR <ulink url="https://github.com/MobilityDB/MobilityDB/pull/833">#833</ulink> — MEOS-WKB byte-format specification.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para><ulink url="https://geoparquet.org/">GeoParquet specification</ulink> — the spatial-Parquet standard this convention is modelled on.</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</sect1>
</appendix>
